Software engineering radio episode 28
type systems.
So in today's episode we're going to
talk about typing.
Uh and this is due to the fact that
we've talked about typing already quite
a lot in um
in the episode about scripting languages
for example. So we figured that it's
better to do uh an episode about typing
exclusively.
You mean typing as in programming
language types not as in hitting keys on
the keyboard.
Yeah, precisely.
So uh the first question is
why should we care about type
You mean why should we care about
typing?
Yeah. And uh one of the reasons is
because uh the types uh define the
expressiveness of a programming
languages uh of a programming language
and uh define what you can actually do
there. Uh the other thing is and that is
also related to the scripting episode uh
scripting languages episode dynamically
typed languages gain more focus recently
and also functional languages uh gain
more focus. It's um sort of um
a wave from aesthetically typed
languages object-oriented languages
towards other different um models and
especially functional languages have a
different and
arguably better typing system.
Um yeah and the other reason for
thinking about this is related to DSLs
and I think that is something that you
are on the way of to say something
about.
Yeah, I mean it is there's a great range
of languages that you can use off the
shelf that you you have compilers that
you have tools for like
C, C++, Java, Smalltalk, Ruby, or
scripting languages, whatever.
And they've got different type systems
and
good to understand the issues of type
systems and of typing in order to choose
the right language for the job, but then
also
writing your own languages,
domain-specific languages is
becoming more and more important. And so
more and more developers find themselves
in a situation
where they are where they where they
actually design their own programming
language and are faced with a challenge
of designing their own type system for
this language.
And this is becoming more and more
important. It's It's not really
mainstream yet, but it's getting there.
And for that it is quite important to or
at least very very helpful to have an
understanding of what type systems are
all about.
So, you know what to do and what not to
do, how to scope your type system if you
write your own programming language.
And the first question, of course, is
what a type actually is.
And
the definition of a type is basically
it's a set of values and operators that
work on them.
So, for example, integers together with
the usual mathematical operations such
as um
addition or um
multiplication it can be considered a
type.
Which is actually quite an interesting
example.
Because for an integer the operations
are well defined. There's consensus as
to what the operations do and more or
less consensus as to what operations
there should be.
But
um different languages have different
ranges of values for an integer.
I think you were just getting to that.
Yeah, and yeah
I mean the the mathematical concept of
an integer is not really limited in
size. It just says it's
a number and that's it.
And
yeah, this is a problem that that type
systems have. Generally speaking,
they're not so clear in
in in what they can express. And
sometimes
even databases, for example, are better
because they, for example, offer strings
with limited length, which is not so
useful in or is not used in normal
programming languages like Java, for
example.
And
also the problem of validation of
data is often rather a type issue
if it was done correctly. So, for
example,
the question really is
can you pass this
The question of
can you pass this string into a date is
really a type issue. It's an issue of
how this
string looks like and if you can't
express that in the type system of the
language, which you usually can't,
then you have to code something yourself
and that's a validation. And the same is
true for limited ranges of certain
numbers and so on. That's all stuff that
could be put into the typing system
while it's usually done in the
validation code.
Yeah, for example, if you want to store
the name of a person,
you usually use a string, but what you
really want is sort of a name type. And
this name type has constraints as to the
characters that can be in it, as to the
minimum length, maybe a maximum length.
And logic what you conceptually want is
to have a name type. You just use the
technical type string and have
validation to enforce these constraints
building on on a string. So, you have a
so some sort of a name type.
And typing comes in different flavors.
Uh so, there is the distinction between
strong and weak typing. So, strong
typing means that uh typing is really
enforced. So, you can't You can only do
operations on certain types if they are
allowed. Uh and weak typing means that
this is basically unchecked. So, for
example,
in a C, a pointer in C
uh is weakly typed because uh it is not
really you cannot really be sure whether
the memory location that uh the C
pointer points to is really uh the type
that you expect. So, you say this is a
pointer to a character,
and you assume that it is actually a
character that is stored there. And it
still works even though if uh there is
an integer that is stored there. And the
other distinction is between dynamically
typed languages and statically typed
languages. So, dynamically typed
language does the type check at runtime,
while statically typed language does the
type check at compile time.
And real languages like C++ for example
are somewhere in between there.
And Java is another example of a
language that is somehow in between
there.
Yeah, an example for a dynamically typed
language for purely dynamically typed
language would be Smalltalk, where you
basically have all where you where you
basically have no type checks at all at
compile time,
and you can send any message to any
object, and if it understands this
message, it can handle it.
And at the end of other end of the
spectrum would be a really strongly
typed statically typed language. Um the
strongest language that comes to my mind
would be Haskell, a functional language
that is
becoming more and more mainstream,
which uh does not have the concept of
type casts, and does a lot with type
inference with type derivation, but
anyway, you can any any program that can
be expressed and passes the the compile
time checks is um sound
from the perspective of the type system.
The language does not permit any um any
that you write anything that would um
lead to a type mismatch at runtime.
And um as we said, Java, for example, is
in between those. So, even though Java
is considered a statically typed
language, this is not the whole truth
because due to the fact that you can
have class casts,
there is still a way of uh tweaking the
type system into accepting some code
that it can't um prove correct. And this
is quite common uh for example, for
collections before JDK 1.5, you had to
type cast the results of the collection
or the content of a collection to a
concrete type, and uh you couldn't
statically check whether this really
really uh this type cast would really
succeed.
Uh so, it's somewhere in between. Um you
still get
uh class cast exceptions in some areas,
but
a lot of stuff is checked already at
compile time.
And it is a strongly typed language
because you get class cast exceptions,
which means that you can't just get um a
string out of uh a collection that only
contains integers,
uh and do an error there. So, that's
detected.
Yeah, actually
in the Java language specification
terminology, there is the distinction
between reference types and object
types.
The object type is the actual type of
the object, sort of a certain location
in memory that represents the data of an
object has a specific type.
But then there is the reference that
points to this location in memory.
And
um those two need not have the same
type. For example,
if we have
an array list in memory, which is a
specific collection class
in Java,
the reference that points to this array
list
can
be of type array list or of type list,
which is a super type, or of type
object, which is the super type of all
types in Java.
So, there there is this distinction, and
at runtime only the object type is used
for type checks. And if the object type
does not
match,
you get a class cast exception if you
try to to cast.
The
compiler only knows about reference
types.
So, all checks are that are done by the
compiler are based on the reference
type.
And if you do a class ca- if you do type
cast, the reference type is changed,
whereas the object type remains the
same.
On the other hand, there are operations
that actually change the object type.
For example, boxing or unboxing,
that is, primitive types are wrapped in
objects or unwrapped, or
the widening of a type. If you pass an
int to a method that expects a long,
then there's an implicit conversion of
the int to the long. That actually
changes the object type. So, Java is a
hybrid language that has concepts from
both worlds.
And well, it's a pragmatic compromise
that works somewhat well,
but
it's a mix of both concepts.
Historically, uh typing was
uh a rather technical term. As we
already said, it's um now more or less
about improving that a program is
correct in terms of the typing, so that
you can have have at least certain
uh check on the program or a proof on
the program.
While historically, it was rather
related to memory allocation, so you
could say, "Okay, a byte is 8 bits and
an integer 16 bits and a long is 32 bits
and so on."
And in languages like C or C++ this was
even dependent on the platform, so uh
depending on which platform you run on,
the
types have uh different different
precision and sizes.
And
this in Java, for example, it's uh
machine independent, but it's still
technology driven. So, the integer is
still somewhat technology driven cuz
it's limited to a certain range of
values,
but it is and it doesn't cover the the
real concept of an integer that is can
be of arbitrary size.
Yeah, actually actually historically,
there were both both trends. The one was
the C kind of language that is close to
the machine, sort of next step beyond
assembly language,
but then in the '50s, just very early
for a programming language, when Lisp
was first thought of, there was the
concept of an unlimited range integer
type. So, both concepts actually go back
back quite a way
and only recently have become have come
closer together due to more powerful
machines that did not make it or make it
less and less necessary for mainstream
programming to be strict about
performance optimization.
And uh Lisp was also the grandfather of
all those functional programming
languages, so that's sort of the reason
why typing systems are better there.
Speaking of functions, functions,
procedures, and methods, and so on, can
also be assigned a type.
And that's rather easy because you can
say the type of a function is defined by
the type of its parameters and the type
of the return value. So, you could say,
"Okay, this function takes an integer
and a string and returns a long." And
this
This is the type of the function. It's a
function that takes those two types of
parameters and returns a different type.
And exceptions can be seen as a possible
return type.
Uh so, you could say instead of an
integer, this method might as well
return an exception. And
You mean return You mean return an
exception by throwing it?
Yeah, exactly. And if you take this
approach, you could argue that uh strong
typing
means that you have to use checked
exceptions because strong typing means
that you must know uh
which kind of return values you can
expect from the function. One kind of
return value that you could expect is an
exception. So, therefore, you need to
have this specifically in uh the
signature of the method, and you need to
take take care about those checked
exceptions.
That's actually quite an interesting
point, and I'd like to point our readers
to the exception handling episode two,
which goes a little bit into these sort
of issues of what different sorts of
exceptions there are and whether to
declare them they make them explicit or
not.
Mm.
But what you what you're describing is
sort of the
um design by contract approach.
A very strict approach that says every
possible outcome of a method needs to be
defined in the contract of the method.
Um
every um
the the preconditions that must be met
by the caller and the postconditions
that the method guarantees. And one of
the possible
um outcomes is that the method should
throw an exception. It needs to be
documented.
That is one valid
way of designing. Definitely, it's very
helpful and very useful.
But it does not enforce checked
exceptions from from my perspective
because
um well, first of all, very few
languages have checked exceptions per
se. I mean, Java has them and more or
less the only language that has checked
exceptions.
And you can even if you don't have
checked exceptions, you can describe it
in the API documentation or wherever
to say under certain circumstances this
or that exception will be thrown.
And then there are lots of exceptions
that can be thrown more or less
everywhere.
Like
invalid parameter exception or
this
pointer was a null and I don't want that
that sort of thing.
And they're sort of implicitly part of
the contract of more or less any method
indicating that there was some sort of
bug.
And there are lots of of of of
situations in between. I don't think we
should really go into that because we
had we dealt with that at length in the
exception handling two episode. But
checked exceptions are quite ambivalent
and you don't really need them to have
this sort of contract.
Yeah, and but this is probably the
reason why
Java came up with checked exceptions.
Whether this is a good idea is, as you
said, beyond this
what we talk about in this episode.
Yeah, exactly.
Functions can have a type, functions can
be passed around as parameters,
functions can be partly evaluated often
and then you have a partly evaluated
function that can be around can be
passed around further, but many
mainstream object-oriented languages do
not have this concept.
I think we should mention that that
although it is conceptually a type, Java
or yeah, well, anyway, Java and C# do
not have this concept of passing around
methods.
In C++ we have something or in C we have
something like that with function
pointers,
which is
not quite the same as in functional
languages, but it's it goes some way.
So,
yeah, this is conceptually very true and
it's a very powerful concept of
functional languages, but mainstream O O
languages currently don't have it. Even
though, for example, inner classes in in
Java, for example, can be used
things that you would usually use
functions for. The The interesting part
of is is signing a function a type is
that you can now do more fancy stuff
like having a parameter a function as a
parameter because you can talk about the
type of the function and therefore
declare
parameters of that type and so on. So,
that's sort of Yeah. The the the stream
Yeah, and uh um
I mean, uh yeah, the mathematical
concept of an integer is it's very
powerful, actually. I was just just
thinking, maybe we should do an episode
on functional programming languages.
I think it's definitely
worth another episode.
Yeah,
absolutely. And this is sort of uh the
this typing episode, I think, is
probably groundwork for for this thing.
So, speaking about So, one thing you
could do that we just discussed is uh
assign functions a type.
One other thing that you can do is to
get more advanced typing stuff is you
could define abstract data types.
What's that?
The The idea here is that instead of
having a type that has certain values
and certain operations that can work on
those values, the values somehow
disappear. So, you are just talking
about operations more or less. So,
operations become the most important
part.
This sounds like the concept of
encapsulation.
Yeah, exactly. That's That's basically
the idea. So, and that's why it's also
why it's called abstract data types. So,
you say it's there is a certain hidden
thing inside this abstract data type
that isn't exported to the rest of the
world.
And the only thing that is exported to
the rest of the world are the operations
that you can do on this type.
And therefore, it's called abstract data
types. And that's sort of the
fundamental for object orientation and
object oriented languages.
That sounds like this is the reason why
it is considered good practice to have
private attributes and define get and
set methods of some kind to access these
attributes even though they're
implemented in a straightforward way and
they're always the same and just change
the attribute or return the value of the
attribute.
Yeah, exactly. That's one of the ideas.
But is it Is that worth it to actually
have these get and set methods that
basically do nothing?
It's This is specific to a language. I
mean, it's
If you do it the the C# way, for
example, this problem more or less
disappears because syntactically you
can't tell whether you're actually
calling a get method or whether you're
really accessing an attribute itself.
It's not so important for typical data
containers. And that's why to a certain
extent there is a problem nowadays
because often you see
systems that are composed of services
and data containers more or less that
don't have much logic in them
themselves.
And it this leads to sort of
the the opposite of abstract data types.
So, you are now separating logic in
services from those data containers. And
that that's somehow not what this
abstract data type and all those stuff
is about.
But it's still a very valid approach
because for example, in service-oriented
architectures or widely distributed
architectures, you want to have data
containers that can be passed around
without any logic because you really
want to have those structures that can
be used in client-server communication
for example.
But originally the idea was different
and the the original idea was to have to
to focus more on the operations and the
stuff that you can do with it.
So, the the key point of abstract data
types is for what I understood you just
said is that you want to have data
hiding, information hiding, you want to
have encapsulation. You distinguish
between the public interface of a type,
the things that are available to the
outside, sort of the API of the type
and the inside that can be changed in
any way and nobody on the on the outside
can know what the inside looks like or
should know. Sort of separation, people
can use the the type and not bother with
the implementation of the type, with the
concrete type.
And this already leads to a certain
problem in this area uh because the
abstract data type is not really a type
because it just it doesn't just define
the operations that you can run on the
type, but it also gives a concrete
implementation most of the time. And
this is also
concrete programming programming
language type like a class is not an
abstract data type in this sense.
Is that what you're saying?
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, because it's a
mixture, especially in in uh now
object-oriented uh languages of
nowadays,
uh this class that you're
that you're implementing is a type
because it defines certain operations,
which is the public interface most of
the time.
And it also defines something more, the
implementation.
So, therefore, class is not really a
type.
An interface is more like a type. That's
basically what it comes down to.
What which is actually a not so old
concept in programming languages. I
mean, looking at C++, C++ does not have
which is one of the older of
object-oriented languages does not have
the concept of an interface.
You can have workarounds like pure
virtual classes, but they're not
first-class members of the of the
concepts of the language really. So,
we're talking about younger languages
mostly like Java or C#.
When you were saying when you were
distinguishing between classes and
interfaces.
Yeah.
And the next thing that you can bring
up, of course, is inheritance or
in terms of of types rather subtyping.
And the rules for subtyping is that
everything the type can be used for the
type is the subtype can be used for as
well.
And you can do additional things. So,
for example, you could say uh there is a
class there is a type a person with
attributes such as name or first name,
and you could say there is a subtype
that is a customer,
and a customer just adds some behavior
and some additional data, like for
example, a rating that you're giving to
the customer, and then everything that
works on a person should also work on
customer.
Uh so, you could add more specific
things, but you must be able to use the
subtype everywhere where the type itself
is used.
Yeah, I think this is a very powerful
concept, and it's very important to get
have a clear understanding of this when
you design actual systems, because it's
um it's very dangerous to just sort of
arbitrarily change the semantics of of
operation calls if you do subtyping.
But then,
playing devil's advocate, I think it is
there are there are situations,
especially if you have some sort of API
evolution of a system that is maintained
over a longer time, uh when you sort of
define a type early on,
publish that, and then want to have
special situations where you want to
change the semantics of the calls.
That happened in for example, in the
Java collection classes. There is the
concept of, let's say, a map, which is a
an associative array. You have keys and
you have values.
And you can put values in there, you can
retrieve them, you can delete them.
And then, later on in a edition of Java,
some of these operations were declared
optional,
so that not all implementations needed
to provide implementations for them. And
then, in an even later version of the
collection API, a new implementation was
provided that compared objects not based
on equality, that is,
well, comparing their values.
This is very becomes very Java-specific.
You can have a method equal that
compares two objects.
And this new implementation compares the
object not based on these equals
implementation equality operation
but on object identity which sort of
breaks every contract. But it's still
very often useful to have the same
interface map for both.
So, I would argue that it's very
important to have this concept of
subtyping clear in your mind but then be
pragmatic about breaking these sort of
constraints when you do subtyping
if you know what you're doing.
Yeah, I think the the the real issue
probably is here is that you have
something out there which is an
interface to system more or less and
it's out there and widely really widely
used and then basically there is no way
of ever changing it.
And that's also the reason why
deprecated methods in Java will never
ever really disappear in the trading
game because you you can't really pay
the effort of migrating away from those
deprecated methods.
Yeah, I'm afraid you're right there.
Yeah, so basically this is sort of
related to the problem that the widely
used interface can not ever be changed
and that's also something that is for
example an issue in service oriented
architectures or web services or things
like that.
Yeah.
Talking about subtyping so you already
gave sort of an example of a subtype for
object oriented systems which is
somehow related to inheritance. So, you
could argue that inheritance
should on the interface level be
subtyping.
This leads to the question what you can
do about the methods.
So
You mean if you have a an abstract type
that defines method that defines
operations and you have a subtype and
what possible things can change in the
in the methods in the operations of the
abstract type if you do subtyping.
Yeah, exactly. Inheritance, what does
that mean for methods?
And the other question more generally
speaking also talking about functional
languages, you could talk about subtype
of functions. So you say there is a
certain type of function that takes
certain parameters as types of
parameters and returns a certain type.
And now you want to have subtype of this
function. What does that look like? It's
basically the same thing whether you
have methods in classes and do
inheritance there or whether you want to
do subclassing in terms of functions.
What you can and because you you still
need to be able to use the subtype
everywhere this the type itself
can be used.
This leads to following.
The parameters the constraints of the
parameters can be relaxed so that way
even though you you think you have the
type itself you can still satisfy the
constraints of the subtype because it
can only relax the constraints of the
types. So every time you satisfy the
constraints of the type itself, you will
also satisfy the constraints of the
subtype.
And for the return value, you can have
more constraints.
So every time you expect
the return value of the type itself, you
can also deal with
the subtype.
You're you're speaking you're speaking
conceptually now of over the things that
are possible from the perspective of
abstract data types and specialization
of abstract data types.
You're not speaking about about concrete
programming languages right now yet at
the conceptual level, right?
Yeah, yeah. And so so it basically comes
down to the fact that a function that
uh takes a person
uh and returns a person, the subtype of
that function might take an arbitrary
object for example as a parameter and
maybe so it relaxes the constraints for
the parameters
and it might return a more specific type
as a return type. So for example, it
might return a customer instead of a
person.
Java does not allow this. Unfortunately,
there are other languages that permit
this sort of thing.
So
concrete programming languages
provide less than the abstract concept
of abstract data types would permit them
to do.
And
um
the other thing that is also quite
interesting is uh
parametric parametric types as an
advanced type
uh thing.
So there you mean the different kinds of
specializing types. One is sort of
subtyping and the other is to in the
supertype to sort of define a parameter
that can make several types out of one
type.
I would argue that those concepts are
really orthogonal. So uh they're
independent of each other. So I would
say that
exactly as you can have as you can have
parameters to functions, you can also
have parameters to types.
And uh that's it basically.
So and it does not
having a parameter to a type does not
necessarily mean that every time you
have a different
type as concrete type as a parameter
uh and get a new
type somewhere. So, basically the idea
first of all is
uh to say, for example, for collections,
there
is not just a collection of
an object or whatever, but rather a
collection of persons
or customers or whatever.
And so, for this you need to have some
means of defining that a list can have
a type parameter and some means to say
in this field in this
piece of code, I want to have a list
that only contains persons or whatever.
Mhm.
And
as we already mentioned
concerning static and dynamic typing
for static typing to actually really
work
you need to have
this in place, permitted parametric
types, because otherwise you can't talk
about collections and type-safe
collections. So, you will always have
sort of
a type leak in the system where you do
dynamically typed stuff.
Well, not necessarily. If you you can
have things like type inference, but may
most languages don't have that. So, for
for practical purposes, you're right.
And we'll talk about type inference just
in a few minutes, I think.
The interesting part is how permitted
types are
implemented.
So, the one that I'm
best familiar with is Java, and in that
case,
it's done with
something that they call type erasure.
So, at runtime in the
bytecode, type is not really present
anymore.
And instead, there are just type casts
at the right location. So, if you say
that it's a list of person, then every
time you take an object out of the list,
uh it's type cast to a person, and uh
the type checker at compile time checks
whether everything is okay with your
code, but it's not present at runtime
anymore.
Yeah, so
This leads to the problem that, for
example, with reflection,
uh it's hard to really get the current
type that is in the list or whatever.
Mhm.
Yeah, this um
using the terminology that we introduced
of the Java language specification,
the object type is knows nothing about
um parametric types.
So, the object types of a list of
strings and of a list of persons is the
same. It's just in the reference types,
they're present at compile time only, so
it's just about compile time checks and
type casts that are introduced.
Then there is the another approach, and
that is fundamentally different. For
example, C++ has this,
which makes
parameterized types sort of a template
that um is
from which a concrete type is made for
every different type that is passed as a
parameter.
In C++, it's just a macro expansion
mechanism, so the compiler actually
compiles the class with a different type
passed in,
creates different object files for them,
and
this is can can be can become really
big. There are more elegant, more
efficient approaches than that,
but nonetheless, it is sort of the real
type approach. If you have the
parametric type in C++, for every
parameter you pass in, for every
different parameter, you get a real
type, a really different type that has,
from the programming language
perspective, no relation at all to the
type with different parameters passed
in.
Yeah, and
in C#,
the type information is actually
contained in the code for the common
language runtime. So, it's again
different, and there is just one
implementation, but that implementation
takes
uh into account the type of unit itself.
Mhm.
But talking about reflection,
with so far we talked about the
perspective of the compiler and of the
runtime environment um to types. And we
have sort of static types that are
available to the compiler, and we have
sort of dynamic types, that is dynamic
type information that is available to
the runtime environment to make type
checks.
But um
going a step beyond that, we have things
like reflection that make type
information available to the program to
the programmer and to the programming
language and to the program at runtime
as well,
which allows them
to well, in the simplest case, read type
information.
We have that in Java, for example.
So, in Java we have possible the
possibility to ask an object, what is
your type?
What is you What are your methods? Your
operations? What are the fields that are
declared? What are the super types? So,
we have read access
to the type structure.
And using reflection, we can invoke an
operation or we can
read a field to read the value of a
field
or set the value of a field.
This is sort of a
it's at odds with having abstract data
types, with having encapsulation,
because it allows access to all the
private internal details of in of a
type,
but it's still a very powerful tool for
dealing with with object structures, to
for dealing with types in a really
generic way.
Having code that can read or write or
create objects just based on the name
information. It's useful for having
generic importers or exporters or having
libraries, frameworks that create
infrastructure services like component
infrastructures or
or persistence infrastructure.
But then there are Yeah?
It's one of the big advantages Java had
over C++ for example.
Yeah.
And more
modern servers infrastructures and also
frameworks like Spring or Java EE can't
just can't work without this in place.
And more recent features like dynamic
proxies for example
even add more to this and in in that
in this case you can have dynamically
um
dynamically react to method calls just
as you can in Smalltalk for example.
So it's sort of
a more dynamic type system even though
there is still a static type
for the
for the compiler in place.
Exactly.
The So it's very powerful feature that
goes way beyond what C++ has. C++
provides things like checks is this is
the same type as that at runtime.
But Java goes way beyond that by
allowing
re-access to the fields, to the
possibility to call operations by name,
creating dynamic proxies or well
annotations are new.
This is what Java and C# and that family
of languages provide as services.
But then there are other languages that
go way beyond that.
Lisp has that
and Ruby has that sort of thing.
Um Smalltalk as well.
These languages allow you to modify your
types at runtime.
So, you can say, "I'd like to have a new
type, and then I'd like to add this
method, and like to add that operation."
And then I'd like to add this field, and
um you can provide So, you know, you can
create and modify the types at runtime.
Types are objects just as any other
object.
And this is what two what what true
reflection really means. When that
allows that is the basis for powerful
frameworks such as Ruby on Rails.
So, again, it proves our point that
typing really defines the expressiveness
of language and
uh what you can actually do with it.
Yeah.
This sort of
um modifying reflective capabilities
were left out of Java consciously
because the creators of Java deemed them
to be well, too powerful a tool to to
give to developers because they allowed
code to be very complicated. They
allowed people to destroy the inner
workings of the language sort of.
And yes, they are very powerful, very
sharp tools which allow you to do much
damage, but then this is a trade-off.
It The more expressive the language is,
the more
um you can do with the language, the
more trouble you can get yourself into.
And uh also for me, one of the reasons
is that Java's really concerned about
security and it's hard to tell what is
actually going on if you allow this kind
of of things.
That's true.
Yeah, that's true.
So,
yeah. So, next point
would be type inference.
And
this is also something that is quite
interesting and is mostly seen nowadays
in functional languages.
Basically, the idea is that you don't
need to declare the types anymore. And
this is somehow strange if you compare
to
uh
usual object-oriented languages where
every
variable has a type assigned.
And what you do instead is that you have
the compiler or whatever
infer the actual type of something. So,
you try to do an operation on something
and
looking at the code, the question is
whether you can
infer that this operation will work
because this thing that you're passing
to this operation is of a certain type.
So, if you say for example, A equals A
plus 1,
you know that A must be an int or
integer or some kind of number.
And looking around, you could now try to
figure out whether the A that you're
talking about at the moment is really a
number in all cases.
And this is sort of
a a complete again a proof on the
correctness of the program and this time
without you having to declare any
uh
additional stuff. So, it's more
automatic.
So, type inference is really a mechanism
for static typing.
It's is it is about
analyzing the code at compile time
and get as much information about the
types out of the code as possible.
So, that the compiler ensures type
consistency
without receiving or without needing
many hints from the programmer.
The idea is that
the compiler uses whatever information
there is
without
help from from the programmer wherever
that is possible.
And actually this concept can go a long
way.
It is um possible
to to have programming languages that
more or less entirely rely on type
inference. Haskell is an example of this
powerful
statically typed um functional language
where basically most types most type
information is derived is inferred from
from the code that is there.
And strangely or for
the type inference is mostly used in
functional languages. So, it's not
really common in object-oriented
languages. Actually, I'm not really
aware of
any real object-oriented language that
uses type inference. I think there was
a Strongtalk
that uh sort of tried that with
Smalltalk, but that's the only thing
that I'm aware of.
Well, there are the new features of C#
3. And in C# 3, there are quite a few um
things going on towards type inference.
Yeah. Well, I think that about wraps it
up for this episode.
Is there anything else you would you
think we should say? Anything else you
think
our readers should hear in this episode
about types and type systems?
Uh well, uh thanks for listening.
Definitely, thanks for listening. Hope
you enjoyed it. We did.
Hear you next time.
Thanks for listening to Software
Engineering Radio. If you want to get
more information about Software
Engineering Radio, or if you want to
give us feedback, please go to our
website at SE-Radio.net.
You can also contact the team at
team@se-radio.net.
Although, we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website, so other
people can see what you think. Software
Engineering Radio wants to thank Henning
Pauli for the intro and outro music, as
well as Lippsons for providing the
bandwidth.
This episode of SE-Radio, as well as all
other episodes, is licensed under
Creative Commons License. See the
Software Engineering Radio website for
details.